[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you think about the thought that having pets increases one's attachments in the world?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the brief answer is, things in the world are not your attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's your attitude towards the things in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, the Buddha said, beautiful things in the world are not man's sensualities, desire and lust towards those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: The sensuality is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people blaming things for their attachment, means people are not seeing where their attachment is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as long as you blame things for your attachment, you're gonna be attached.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the most natural response is, when people think, I must give up the attachment, is to throw away all my possessions and get rid of everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not freeing you from attachment, that's just obscuring your attitude that you had towards those things, which means, when something else comes your way, you're going to be equally attached to it, because you haven't undermined that, eh... a mental stance of appropriation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in terms of pets or family members, parents, like, your attachment is your emotional dependence upon those things being present in the world, not those things in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if truly you would need to get rid of the stuff to be free from attachment, means you need to go and destroy the whole world to be free from attachment to the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are some things, some relationships not worthy of having.
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, sensuality in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, if you want to have pets, in this particular example, well, before you do, ask yourself why.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you having pets because you genuinely want to help animals?
[SPEAKER_03]: We are having pets because you're feeling lonely, or bored, or you need... you need excitement, or some novelty, or just a cute little pet.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is...
[SPEAKER_03]: Most people don't think this through.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why, like, the shelters are full of abandoned animals in the West.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because people would take them in a... in a spur of a moment, and then afterwards, basically, when that kind of novelty runs out, you realize it's... it's... it's too demanding, too much care, too... it takes too much time, too much effort, too much responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you just give them, well, the places that sort of provide it, but really what you do is just make it someone else's problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that all could have been prevented if you were...
[SPEAKER_03]: A bit more self-reflexive before you commit it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, you have, like, things that... like your parents or your family, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have no choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't, you know, can't give them away.
[SPEAKER_03]: And... so... so that's why you... sometimes you're bound with things that kind of create attachment for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it doesn't mean that you're not responsible for the attachment part.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you're not responsible for being paired with these people, or those, this, your family, or, or, or, or, or so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you are responsible if you're emotionally attached upon it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you think that you can free yourself from attachment just by dismissing these people, or these things in the world, you're so... you have, like, seriously mistaken, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: The attachment, giving it up, it's much subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody has a pet,
[SPEAKER_01]: And they see that they are quite emotionally attached to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What should they do if they want to free themselves from it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, basically, they should contemplate the death of that pet as much as they can.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without abandoning it, without stopping, like, withdrawing care for it and helping it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you just have to keep reminding yourself to the point of view where you become sort of... when you go emotionally above it, above the thought that this thing, that this pet, this friend or whatever, whatever attitude you have towards it, it's gonna go.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will go.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might die even before it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it will...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where people are kind of either-or.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either I'll be fully invested emotionally or I'll completely dismiss it and throw it away and not have anything to do with it because I'm afraid of my attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: The fact that you're afraid you might get attached means you're not free from possibility of attachment, means you're not free from nature of attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, like, you might... you can give away the pet.
[SPEAKER_03]: There'll be other things you're then attached... attached to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, really, you want to recognize the problem and then see, okay, there are certain things that are not necessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: A certain degree of involvement is not necessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you've been doing it purely out of attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, when you became aware of the attachment, you will naturally withdraw yourself to a certain degree.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there is no blanket rule how much you must be withdrawn from the world and from your engagements.
[SPEAKER_03]: Different people measure these things differently.
[SPEAKER_03]: The engagement means different things for them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or some people can take more of it, some people can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that should not be the criteria, like how many pets you have, for example, or how many charities you support.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, criteria should be how much of the attachment is there in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in regard to animals still, do you think it's best to leave them alone?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not interfere as a human being?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think there's a universal law.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can do whatever you like, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't mean you won't pay the price for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If, you know, if you're in a position to help, why wouldn't you?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, even the Buddha himself said, giving even to an animal, or not even to a specific animal, just throwing away food and saying, may those animals and creatures that feed on this food, feed on this food that I've thrown away, that will bring you merit and sort of like a good reward for your actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let alone, let alone helping, helping, helping humans or helping greater number of animals and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, you don't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to do any of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, you must help.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But aren't they... some people think that animals are happier when they're not around human beings.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, they might think that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what they should do is ask themselves, why do they think that?
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're probably going to find out that they think it because they want to find a justification for them not helping animals in the first place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when they are in a position to do... when they wouldn't even necessarily be attached to it, even to help them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they still don't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then they would find, oh, well, that's whatever they say, that's their karma, they deserve it, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's just ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if they do deserve it, that still has nothing to do with you choosing to not help somebody in need of help, animal or human, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, if you don't help, yeah, you don't have to feel guilty.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's, you know, it's really up to you to do whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you're self-honest, and if you question your motive, you'll see that usually, not helping is rooted in unwholesome motives.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either ill-will or dismissal, can't be bothered, can't... can't...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't care, or too lazy, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you're aware of it, you wouldn't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about neutering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh, eh, eh, listen, listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: What about neutering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutering the animals?
[SPEAKER_01]: The animals, your pets, so they can't have... they can't poke you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, to answer that question, obviously, it would... depends what point of view you come from.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, obviously, as somebody who practices the dhamma, and a Buddhist person, it's probably the best thing you can do to an animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because animals stay animals, as in, they remain bound to central... animal central realm, because all their thoughts, all their actions revolve around senses, around animal intentions, around cravings, sexuality, food, fighting.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is constantly driven.
[SPEAKER_03]: And because of that, it's so hard to break out of the animal rebirth.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_03]: It takes like a blind... similar of a blind turtle coming up to the top of the sea, top of the ocean, once every 500 years.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there is a yoke, a piece of wood with a hole in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's being sort of thrown and floating left and right, thrown by the winds and the waves.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this blind turtle that comes from the bottom once 500 years, has a greater chance of sticking its head through that hole in that little piece of wood.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's being thrown constantly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, a being that has fallen into an animal realm, has a chance of coming back to human realm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you look at them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever they do, it's bound with the animal realm entirely.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they cannot have things, sort of, eh... like a... of a loftier nature that would then result in a... in a higher rebirth.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why neutering is good is because animals can't restrain themselves.
[SPEAKER_03]: The only way they can restrain themselves if... if... is if that's... that restraint is placed externally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind you, that's true for most of the humans.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, we are speaking about animals.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, the lucky animal is the one that has proper restraint placed upon it, externally, as in, by a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like violence.
[SPEAKER_03]: No violence, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, neutering them, as we've done with these dogs, you saw the massive difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, they don't think about sexuality anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you do remember, when they did think about it, well, like a madness would come over their mind, which means all the actions they'll be committing on account of it are very, very unwholesome, and they have no... they don't have enough self-reflection to see that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in a way, they're victims, but they're victims of their own actions, and that's why it keeps perpetuating itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the... a lucky dog, for example, or a cat, or whatever, the one that you neutered, means you took that very powerful, unwholesome dimension out of their existence, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sexuality, craving, fighting, I mean, raping, it's horrible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when they get into their mate in the heat, it's just violent.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you look on the roads and streets, and they lose perspective as well, completely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come back malnourished, ripped apart, because they were fighting for dominance and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything, just unwholesome on top of the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, you're new to them, and that whole dimension is gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: They can't even think about it anymore, let alone act upon it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you could see that in an animal realm, which could be considered a darker realm, as in all the actions are bound with sensuality, and ill-will, and craving, and fear, and so on, having an absence of the same amount of bad actions can actually mean a lot of positive.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, what the Buddha said, in the darker realms, even just like a fleeting thought, a positive thought, even very fleeting in the nature, can mean a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there isn't any.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it will really stand out and it could then bring those beings back up to higher realms, where they can become aware of their self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, consequently, that's why the Buddha said the people who live their life unrestrained, don't even keep the five precepts and basically just follow every single desire that they have, scratch, ditch, whenever it itches, they're no different than animals and usually that's the realm they're heading, their behavior is taking them to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you just react upon any impulse that comes your way and completely are unaware, due to your own obscuring, unaware of the responsibility that you actually inherently carry for your own choices and your own freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: People don't have to help anyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you should really ask yourself, if you choose not to help, well, ask yourself why, why did you make that choice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why was it rooted?
[SPEAKER_03]: Was it rooted in carelessness, laziness, hatred, whatever?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just find it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is there any other way that you could help animals, if you wanted to, other than neutering them?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you might want to do that as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I think, obviously, just providing, like feeding them, for example, means they'll be less on a
[SPEAKER_03]: On that verge of hunger, they will make them edgy, and in a fighting mode, and greedy, and stealing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: All these are wholesome things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, vaccinations.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you help them, obviously, like, if you can, by shelter, providing shelter, providing medicine, providing food.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, if you have the ability, train them a bit.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just make them wait for the food.
[SPEAKER_03]: Literally, that's something that people could benefit from.
[SPEAKER_03]: I eat whenever I feel an urge to put something in my mouth, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not when I'm hungry.
[SPEAKER_03]: And actually, the Buddha did say that in one of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: That in some regards, animals are actually more virtues than most of the, like, the contemporary people at the time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they would mate only when there was basically a season, when a female would be in a season.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, at the time, when they were saying that, you would have these rich people, would have, like, many wives, and just constantly having sexual intercourse, left and right, without a purpose, just with... sole purpose... sole purpose was sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: The other thing that the Buddha did say was, in regards to the same sort of sutta, was the... yeah, like the animals would eat when they're hungry, the dogs, but then you had people like accruing wealth and just not sharing and just eating whenever they wanted, just hoarding it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being greedy, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in that regard, animals are more restrained.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, obviously, you know, sexuality is a big part in every being's sort of life, and certainly can be a great motivator, which always results in unwholesome proliferation of desire, which is then responsible for your rebirth and actions you committed on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, just helping animals in that sense, you would basically prevent the whole domain of attachment for them, on account of which you'll be doing lots and lots of unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, even for a female dog, as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, first of all, you help her not going through that whole process of being basically gang-raped by the bunch of... by a pack of dogs, which is how... it might not happen when people are kind of carefully breeding dogs, but when you look out on the road, it's like ten males, and it's just battlefield.
[SPEAKER_03]: For two weeks, you're just crying and abused.
[SPEAKER_03]: Horrible.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, on top of it, puppies, children, are the greatest attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's no different for animals.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people think, oh, you're depriving these animals of happiness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that happiness is just like one percent, on top of the ninety-nine percent of pain and exposure to pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just that she can barely fend for herself and provide for herself, like a stray dog, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, she seeks puppies to feed.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you see that, when you see the stray dog with puppies.
[SPEAKER_03]: When she starts breastfeeding, it just turns into this completely emaciated sort of skeleton, like within a week.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they don't get enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you think that's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's pleasant for the dog and for the puppies.
[SPEAKER_03]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a torture.
[SPEAKER_03]: And most of the puppies will end up dying.
[SPEAKER_03]: And probably the mother as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: If she doesn't die, clearly, it's going to take her like half a year to recover, to have the fur back and health back.
[SPEAKER_03]: By which time, she's going to get pregnant again.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then again.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's just a constant sort of being subjected to just a constant pressure and striving and greed and fear and fighting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you remove that, then it's just a happy dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what if your dogs get very sick?
[SPEAKER_01]: And one of them are in a lot of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no cure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you consider euthanasia?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: They'll die anyway.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're all gonna die anyway.
[SPEAKER_03]: If a dog were to have a choice to do it itself, yeah, I wouldn't interfere with it either.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means you'll be killing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it was a lot of pain?
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the pains that you can perceive in someone else's dying might not be anything in comparison to the pains of a being actually dying.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, like, it might look painful, but it's still alive.
[SPEAKER_03]: But when it actually starts dying, that's the worst type of pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is according to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: But usually people judge this situation based on how they feel.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I can't bear to watch this, so I'll kill it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Compassionately.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll put it out of my misery.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll put it out of my misery, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's that's how you should read.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, again, you can do whatever you want, but don't deceive yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are killing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what about, like, dog shelters?
[SPEAKER_01]: They get all these stray dogs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they're killing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: 20,000 dogs.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're killing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I mean, obviously, they're responsible for the act of gassing them, and whatever means they use, but whoever gives their dog to a shelter, is also responsible for killing them.
[SPEAKER_03]: If they end up being killed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they wouldn't have ended up being killed if you didn't put them in a shelter that kills dogs.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Think twice before you actually choose to act and commit and do things in any area of life.
[SPEAKER_03]: But people's judgment, basically, it's usually emotional, which is not really a judgment.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more a reaction.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, I'm only going to look at the reasons for having it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not gonna stop and think about and maybe be patient and see if I change my mind or if I really thought this through.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not just for the pets, in general, in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the attitude, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another question that usually comes up for a lot of people is, how can monastics be withdrawn from sensual pleasures if they are using the internet?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's... the internet for... it's a very sensual thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you use it for that particular reason.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, Internet is a tool.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you use tool to gain sensuality, yeah, but you don't blame the tool, you blame your own sensual intentions and your own sensual actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot engage in sensuality without having, sort of, without perceived it as a central desire, as a central outcome that you want to pursue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means sensuality is always intentional.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't accidentally stumble, like, engage in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the question here, it's not like whether you should use the internet or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: The question is, are you restrained or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're not restrained, then, yeah, you should foresee these circumstances, they might tempt you further, and then you avoid it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But even then, you don't place responsibility on avoidance of these things, because the real problem is you not having uprooted sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you might avoid Internet all you want, but you can still spend your time with sensual thoughts, sensual cravings, living on top of a mountain, and be equally bound by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, one day, you have to use the internet again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, sooner or later, something will happen, where you're going to be exposed to things that used to cause you, basically, sensual desire, and you're going to have it again, because you haven't done anything about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't spend your whole life in hiding.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there was that very nice sutta, the simile of the bait, the deer herd, that the Buddha talks about, where like most people would... the hunter places the food that has a bait in it, and that's basically like a description, a simile for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: It baits you to become sort of engaged with it and attached, just because of that promised pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the most people would be sort of careless, and they would just be eating it together with a bait.
[SPEAKER_03]: They wouldn't even see it as a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: They wouldn't even see the bait.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, a group of people would recognize that, and then say, well, okay, we need to restrain ourselves, because that's basically... but they can't draw a line between a food and the bait, so then they dismiss the entire domain of food.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they, as Buddha said, they're like a deer herd that runs on top of a mountain, and then they live lives there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But sooner or later, the food will... whatever they've been living on in the mountain will dry out, and then they will come back to the same environment that they despised, and they would eat carelessly, they wouldn't see the bait, and they would remain the same as the first herd.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the third one would be basically the one who's seen the first, seen the second.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then realize, actually, we must not shun the food.
[SPEAKER_03]: We just have to learn how to eat it carefully, without engaging with the bait, without being hooked.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that refers to basically avoiding sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like flirting with sensuality and carefully, so you don't get... No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flirting with sensuality means you're basically already hooked.
[SPEAKER_03]: But learning how to eat carefully or, in other words, learning how to be restrained and seeing where your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, people would blame the food, blame the internet, blame this, blame the city, blame the environment, but that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem is your attitude of sensuality in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you recognize that that's on you, you exercise restraint to the right degree.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you could see genuinely, oh, this is a tool.
[SPEAKER_03]: This can be used wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, this cannot be used wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things like sexual intercourse, they're fully already perverted by the desire, which means you can't do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to abandon it altogether.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if a person does have problem with the restraint, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Minimize your exposure to things that are challenging you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, don't project your responsibility onto those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to see it and then you have to see what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem is not the Internet.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem is not the central objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem is your sensuality in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're not going to approve that just by dismissing the central objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or the object that could potentially result in sensual outcome.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you start clarifying that, then, yeah, then you are developing enough space, basically, to see and to move about without taking things up in sensual manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become quite strong, because you can withstand the possibilities.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, not just withstand, you actually uproot it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The possibility of you sensually engaging in sensual possibilities.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when you know you're beyond sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like no amount of sensual
[SPEAKER_03]: Objects would become a temptation anymore, because the mind has fully seen and discerned the danger of sensuality and the inherent, basically, repulsiveness of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being a victim to your own desire, you fully understood that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's... and by doing so, you have abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you can't actually engage with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, like, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha would say it's like as if a man would sort of eat some delicious food and then he would vomit it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, like, would he have a desire to eat that vomit again?
[SPEAKER_03]: He just wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: You'd be repelled by the thought of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you said earlier about how to overcome attachments, like to your dogs or to your pets, I mean, that to contemplate the possibility, the inevitable possibility of their death, to free you from attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: When I say contemplate, I mean allow yourself to emotionally feel the significance of those things, not like explain to yourself
[SPEAKER_03]: Just basically to appease your own emotional disturbance, at the thought of your favorite pet dying or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, don't go, they all die and then you start explaining.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You actually want to take it on that emotional level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, to not be afraid to feel the death of the loved ones.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that will basically pressure your mind into growth.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your mind will have to grow out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or it will have to succumb to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It reminds me of what you're saying this morning about being intoxicated with youth, intoxicated with health, intoxicated with life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's, it's... Well, take it for granted, your own life, you start taking for granted lives of other things, beings, animals or humans, which means death, even a notion of it, is going to be frightening.
[SPEAKER_03]: To you, to your emotional equilibrium, it's going to be a challenge.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unless you recognize that as a problem, you can't sort of grow out, you can't develop yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you've got all of your efforts will be about covering it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, we all died and none of that, all of that is done just to prevent you from taking it on personally.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you start questioning, basically, just... well, the validity of that assumption, like, why do I...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, yeah, we will all die, so why don't I imagine that I might be dead by this afternoon, or maybe even tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, why would I... why would I just assume that my life is ahead of me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or my health?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or my youth?
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you start questioning those things on the level of yourself,
[SPEAKER_03]: It means you are automatically affecting any attachment that you have depending upon those things in regard to others.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, if you become fully aware of your own mortality, you cannot be attached to other person's life.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't mean you become like a blind, oblivious, robotic creature.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you're still full aware of the significance of life, of helping animals, or caring after people, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: But none of that causes that emotional intoxication of assumption that this will last forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means when it changes, when it goes away different to the way you expected it and hoped for, you won't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your perspective will remain, basically, eh... undiminished.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just would not change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it wasn't dependent upon that anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the true meaning of being free from attachment and freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like not recognizing the significance of, you know, dying loved ones or something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the contrary, being fully able to let it arise to the extent it wants to arise and you won't have to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to jump into grief, break down into tears, nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're able to hold it and keep perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: As those enlightened people in the suttas would say, like, how could it be otherwise?
[SPEAKER_03]: When they were facing somebody dying, their good friend or mother, father, whatever, it would be just like, like, how could it be otherwise?
[SPEAKER_03]: How could a thing that has a reason not die?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's no surprise.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't surprise.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's... well, it's surprising to think that it can be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a surprise.
[SPEAKER_03]: For those who cannot think that anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's very much a lot of stoicism, very much in this think about pre-meditate, think about death, think about loss of health, aging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the right thinking, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: The right thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: People think right thoughts will come out spontaneously out of some sort of magical experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right thoughts will come up if you stop engaging, nurturing and maintaining the wrong thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the wrong thought is any thought of greed, aversion, delusion, any thought that is based upon assumptions, that perpetuates these gratuitous assumptions and intoxications.
[SPEAKER_03]: With your life, with your health...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, people think, just like, when they're healthy, you think you're never gonna get sick.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, just the thought that you might get sick, freaks you out all the way.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like nothing... there's no... no... no safe zone in between.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like when people get a flu, they just full-on panic.
[SPEAKER_03]: They want every medicine from the shelf, doctor to give them, just... just to get rid of this discomfort, because it's threatening to my existential assumption of... of an indefinite health.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or a pimple on the face.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: A pimple on the face or a... Or a hair going the other way you don't want it to go or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just interfering with your perception of yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's like bothering you on that existential level.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's not like... it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't remain indifferent towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are being emotionally oppressed.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're doing it yourself, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: By maintaining those assumptions, when they're challenged by the circumstances of the world, they go against your desires, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot remain indifferent.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are affected.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, suffering is, as the Buddha described, in the most general terms, basically, not getting what one wants and being paired with things that one doesn't want.
[SPEAKER_03]: In brief, basically, there's five aggregate ties.
[SPEAKER_03]: In your experience as a whole, attachment to it, in any shape or form, that's why suffering is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, I was going to ask this question, you touched on it there, is how to improve your thinking?
[SPEAKER_01]: How to make your thinking clearer and right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about the right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deeply.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first step is to get a hint, at least, that actually this might be a valuable thing to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Learn how to think properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, if you do, then you can start looking closer at it and basically see what is... what are the things that are sort of against right mindful thinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Essential desire is.
[SPEAKER_03]: By giving in to essential desire, to the emotional needs, you are compromising your own reason.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, some people do more, some people do less, but nevertheless, that's in common to every time you give in to desire or need for emotional satisfaction,
[SPEAKER_03]: For sensual satisfaction, to that degree, you compromise your reason, you compromise your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you're actually contemplating and premeditating how to engage in sensuality, that's not done in that rightful manner, because it's not founded upon mindfulness and self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are projected towards the project of sensuality or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, recognizing what goes against calm, composed, mindful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Clarity, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Foggy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Foggy, obtuse, opaque, whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's all against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, ill-will, anger, it's against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Engaging in angry behavior, cultivating ill-will and hatred, you are basically obscuring your own perspective on yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same with distraction, in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just want to do something because you're bored.
[SPEAKER_03]: Boredom is actually clarity.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people fear it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it reveals things that you don't want to admit to yourself, yet they're always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why people always need things to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Existentially, they depend upon constant performing of action and finding meaning in random things, just to make them do stuff, because it basically keeps you floating, or so it seems.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you run out of things to do, if you run out of even the most frivolous purpose, you basically feel like you begin to sink.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the problem with that whole
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole view is that sooner or later you won't be able to do things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what you're going to have left is that which you've been running away from your whole life.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why old age is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body stops listening, you lost your health, you lost your strength, you lost your youth.
[SPEAKER_03]: The senses are failing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't get distracted now through beautiful sights.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't even appreciate it anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just hurts to look, hurts to hear it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not pleasant eating.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what you're left is yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what you're left with.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's something you didn't want to be with your whole life.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why you've been using the intoxication with health, youth, and life, and sensuality in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just to keep sort of surfing on top of it, without having to face what's underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a lot of clarity, awareness, constant awareness, can be very painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said boredom is very painful because of clarity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, clarity is not painful, but it reveals the painful background.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that background is painful only because you're resisting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Only because your habits of your life, the ones you've been engaging with, are the ones that are taking you away from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Namely, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just following your desires for granted, wanting to have whatever your desire basically directs you... directs you at, and because of that, not engaging in that behavior is deemed painful.
[SPEAKER_03]: You create the pain of boredom.
[SPEAKER_03]: As in boredom.
[SPEAKER_03]: You create the boredom because you don't want it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Boredom in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry, it's neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you understand neutral feeling, it is felt as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you don't understand it, as in, if you're still basically affecting it with assumptions and and and and preconceived notions and habits of sensuality, then it's going to feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling nothing is going to feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's going to feel threatening, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you have any practices to clear one's thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, physical restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not engaging in distracted behavior, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not engaging in, basically, like... Yeah, you have to stop, for example, drinking, being careless, taking drugs, because that, certainly, it's directly opposed to any clarity that you can maintain in your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, at the same time,
[SPEAKER_03]: You also have to understand that the real clarity comes from understanding what clarity is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not from what feels clear.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's inevitable at the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: We all start based on how we feel, but you want to transcend that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't want to just be bound by how you feel and what you deem pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if people don't understand the clarity, then they're just going to be pursuing that which they think clarity is, which is that which they deem agreeable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not necessarily understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when you have people overdoing the practice of clarity, trying to catch every single moment and things like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, to catch a moment, you have to be outside of that moment.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you're outside of that moment, that moment is not in your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're just chasing these hollow, contradictory ideas on account of developing clarity.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, clarity is basically absence of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: If those things are not present in your experience, you don't have to then get rid of whatever else is present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because all you care about is the unwholesome aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: But people usually can't see where the line is, so then they try to dismiss it all.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, when we spoke just earlier,
[SPEAKER_03]: Attachment is a problem, so I'll throw away everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Baby and the bathwater.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm attached to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I must destroy it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I must give it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how I free myself from my attachment, what you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the Buddha realized that when he came to the point of even trying to give up his own life, because thinking that's the way out, but then he realized it wasn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's only gonna result in me dying, unenlightened.
[SPEAKER_03]: When he tried to stop his own breathing, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, well, I'm breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm helping this life that's a
[SPEAKER_03]: Unfortunately, he didn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: He saw through it and then he realized that actually, no, it's only resulting in me being dead.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, abandon things that are unnecessary, with basically a full proliferation of carelessness in regard to sensuality, ill-will, restraint and moderation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, try to understand that clarity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't overdo it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about concentrating on a neutral object?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that take away all the unwholesome objects?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, no, because concentration for people today means absorption.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you're absorbed into something, means you're not aware of yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how can you develop self-reflection and self-clarity, if the basic premise of yourself being present and seeing that in the situation is not there?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why most of the contemporary meditation techniques are completely misleading.
[SPEAKER_03]: No doubt that the novelty experiences and peace come out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that peace is also peace at the cost of self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means it's a peace that's peaceful only because it's agreeable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because it's a genuine clarity or contains wisdom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's only because I find it agreeable.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why often it ceases to be enough as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then people need to do it harder, commit harder, to get more of that novelty back that's going to be a peaceful feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not the peace you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's basically peace within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about the power of concentration?
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't want power of concentration.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want power of reflection.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the right concentration will come out of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't, again,
[SPEAKER_03]: When a person is committing to some practice of concentration on account of their muddled and foggy and obtuse thinking, no clarity of their thinking can arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's basically... the tools they're using to develop their concentration are the ones affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you're not seeing that, whatever you gain through them is just going to share the same nature.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because people think that, well, as long as I practice concentration of any kind, that will transfer itself and I'll benefit from it in other, like, spiritual development.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't.
[SPEAKER_03]: That development that you think is spiritual, it's really, like, sensual.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is why, yeah, most people's practice of spirituality is very much sensual.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a practice of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attaining physical experiences.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically attaining agreeable experiences without trying to see your motivation behind it or like fully understanding the nature of those experiences.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you could say that any spiritual practice today, it's basically just spiritualizing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: The true spiritual practice comes in you undoing the sensuality, and then seeing what's there already, without you needing to have a desire for it, or inspiration, or whatever, some sort of spiritual uplifting.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why, that's why, if the dhamma is done rightly, the Buddha's teaching is done rightly, like, nobody can stumble upon it by accident or through some miraculous experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's done through development.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's achieved through development and basically hard work.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the Buddha would just praise the diligence, self-reflection, not tolerating unwholesome states that you know are present in you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're tolerating them.
[SPEAKER_03]: By tolerating them, you give rise to motivation that's rooted in them.
[SPEAKER_03]: By giving rise to that, sooner or later you're going to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you end up being fully responsible for the perpetuation of your own ignorance and lack of freedom.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's going on?
[SPEAKER_02]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_03]: There's not enough room.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is Jābū visible?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not really, eh?
[SPEAKER_03]: I only have one lap.
Come on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on, get up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get up.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's coming.